Guide to the Elizabeth Crook Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Elizabeth Crook Papers
1984-2000
The Wittliff Collections
Crook, Elizabeth, 1959-
SWWC.060
19 Linear Feet
31 boxes
Research notes, annotated typescripts, correspondence, photographs, and newsclippings make up the Elizabeth Crook papers, and relate mainly to Crook's novels of historical fiction, Raven's Bride (1991), and Promised Lands: A Novel of the Texas Rebellion (1994). The collection is arranged into the following three series: Works, Mailing Lists, and Clippings.
Scope and Contents
Research notes, annotated typescripts, correspondence, photographs, and newsclippings in the Elizabeth Crook papers range in date from 1984-2000, and relate mainly to Crook's novels of historical fiction, Raven's Bride (1991), and Promised Lands: A Novel of the Texas Rebellion (1994).
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Crook, 1995 and 2001.
Biographical Notes
Elizabeth Crook was born in 1960 in Nacogdoches and raised in San Marcos, Washington DC, where her father directed VISTA (Volunteers in Service to America) under Lyndon B. Johnson, and Australia, where her father served as ambassador. Crook went on to Baylor University, and received her B.A. in English from Rice University.
In 1985, she began intensely researching what would become an article in the Southwestern Historical Quarterly (July, 1990), focused on the 1828 marriage of Tennessee governor Sam Houston and the 20 year old Eliza Allen. This article became the touchstone of her best-selling first novel, Raven's Bride, published in 1991 by Doubleday. The 750 page manuscript was accepted by the publisher after fifteen publishing houses had rejected it; Crook's soon-to-be editor at Doubleday, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, called her personally to accept it. Journalist and author Bill Moyers writes that in Raven's Bride, Crook "brought to life the great events of Texas past and turned them into a robust novel. The characters, the descriptions, and the drama are a panorama that only a fine historian or inspired novelist could handle to the reader's delight, and Ms. Crook is both."
In 1993, Crook was inducted into the Texas Institute of Letters. A year later, she published her second novel, Promised Lands: A Novel of the Texas Rebellion, also edited by Ms. Onassis at Doubleday. "At a time when war is sanitized, televised, and intellectualized, Crook's most important contribution may be her reminder of the insanity and sheer waste of it all… Though she probably did not intend it that way, her account of the slaughter at Goliad is one of the most powerful anti-war statements I've read" (Joyce Slater, Houston Post).
Crook currently lives in Austin, with her husband, Marc Lewis, a professor of psychology at the University of Texas, and their son.
Texas -- Politics and government -- Fiction; Historical fiction; Women authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Literature; Crook, Elizabeth, 1959-; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994
- Raven's Bride, 1984-1990, undated
  Series Description
  This series includes extensive research files and many annotated typescripts of Crook's first novel. The research files include clippings, handwritten notes, photographs, and correspondence with research assistant Eva B. Denning, of Gallatin, TN, 1984-90. The typescripts have been arranged in alphabetical order by working titles.
  - Research
    - Allen, Eliza and family (Box 1, Folder 1-3, Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Architecture (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bledsoe, Anthony (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Boyers, Blackmore (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Campbell, John B. / Cryer (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cantrell, Stephen / Cannon, Newton (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Carroll, William (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Customs (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Douglass Family (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Eaton, John H. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Fashions (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Foster, Robert C. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Gallatin, TN (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Grundy, Felix (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Guild, Judge Jo. C. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hall, William (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Horse breeding (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hume, Reverend William (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jackson, Andrew (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Lewis, William B. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Maps (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Martin, Robert and Robert McEwen (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - McGregor, General John (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Morris, Eastin (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Nashville (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Overton, John (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Peyton, Bailie (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Polk, James (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Saunders / Donelson (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Shelby, Isaac (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Simon, Monkey (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Trousdale family (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Tyree, Clayton (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Williams, Willoughby (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - White, W. and G. B. Williams (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Typescripts
    - "Notions of Honor"
      - Mary Beth's manuscript, circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - "Runaway Scrape"
      - Annotated typescript, pages 1-284, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Annotated typescript with bibliographic notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 4, Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - "Sam Houston and Eliza Allen"
      - Synopsis, with bibliographic notes, 47 pages (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Synopsis, with bibliographic notes, 66 pages (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 5-6, Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Without a Stone"
      - Annotated typescript, revised, December 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2-4)
      - Typescript, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 4-5, Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Old version, undated (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 3-5, Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 4, Box 13, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Untitled
      - Typescript (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Typescript fragments (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
      - Annotated draft, pencil and blue ink, undated (Box 15, Folder 4-5, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 3-5)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
      - Typescript fragment, includes 1981 photo (possibly of Crook), 1981, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Annotated draft, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-3, Box 20)
    - Raven's Bride, undated
      - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 21, Folder 5, Box 22, Folder 1-2)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 22, Folder 3-5)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
      - Photocopied final proof, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Afterword typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Annotated page proofs (with blue notes) (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
  - Annotated galleys (with blue notes) (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
  - Annotated galley (photocopy) (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Mock-up with typesetting annotations (Box 24, Folder 4-5)
  - Computer disks (6 5.5" floppy) "Sept-Oct. bound galleys" (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Computer disks (6 5.5" floppy, 2 3.5" 1 Mb) chapter drafts (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Dustjacket quotes from Liz Carpenter and James Michener (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Book design correspondence and proposed illustrations, 1989-1990 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Publicity correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1990-1994 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Promised Lands, 1990-1994, undated
  This series includes research files and annotated typescripts of Crook's second novel. The typescripts have been arranged in alphabetical order by the various working titles. Correspondence includes a letter from John Graves commenting on Promised Lands, editorial correspondence with Jackie Onassis, and correspondence regarding publicity. Also includes one black and white publicity photo of Crook by Dan Flores.
  - Research notes and correspondence, 1990, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Typescripts, 1993, undated
    - Gates of the Presidio, annotated typescript (Box 25, Folder 8, Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Goliad (includes note from Crook to Harrigan), undated (Box 26, Folder 2-4)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 26, Folder 5, Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Promised Lands, annotated typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 2-6)
    - Revisions after Jackie Onassis' suggestions, January 20, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 7, Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings and reviews, 1993-1994 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 28, Folder 4)
- Essays and Articles, 1994-1995, undated
  Typescripts of three articles by Crook.
  - Remembering Jackie Onassis, My Editor (Publishers Weekly, June 27, 1994) typescripts; Tribute to Mary Elizabeth Holdsworth Butt given by Elizabeth Crook on March 26, 1995, typescript; Crossing Over (essay on Barton Springs), typescript, June 27, 1994, March 26, 1995, undated (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Mailing Lists, undated
  The mailing lists in this series include personal and business contacts, as well as lists for publicity purposes, such as newspaper lists.
  - Mailings Lists (Box 28, Folder 6)
- Clippings, 1990-2000
  This series includes news clippings, reviews, and select editorial correspondence, as maintained by Crook
  - Photocopies, 1990-2000 (Box 29)
  - Originals, 1990-2000 (Box 30, Box 31)